I'm Mark Clement and I'll be doing the review. And Linda Cave is out at the table.
She has a lot, she can answer any questions about logistics, about the course.
So she's best to ask on that. Usually if you have an ask question, I'll just refer you to her.
So just go to her first. She'll be here today and probably tomorrow and probably Sunday,
but I'm not an exacted sir on Sunday. She may or may not be here.
You should have in your possession a blue and yellow book.
If you don't and you didn't register, you need to go out and register now and get that done.
I'd like to thank Shannon and Derek for all their work getting us organized.
It's what you do. It's a lot of work. I appreciate it.
Amazingly, it's just like two weeks time. I know professional event planners that can't pull off anything.
They have six months. You guys ought to go into event planning if you don't pass your board.
We're number three.
The lights, we don't know anything about the lights.
No, I tried getting them back on.
We have some function with the lights. Are they even trying or did they just say?
They come on and immediately go back on.
So they're not going to try and fix it?
Not this weekend.
So we're going to be... Now is that sunlight? Or is that ambient light?
Lighting is not light.
Is that not light up?
That's true. I was going to say if that's sunlight, when it goes down, it's going to be a little dark.
Hopefully it's just backlighting. Do you think that's what it is?
Yeah, I think so.
Okay, good. Well, that'll give us some lighting.
My eyes actually are... When I first came in here, they seem pretty dark in here, but it actually starts a lot lighter.
I guess I'm accommodating. So you'll have to take notes in this light.
I apologize for that, but that's just the way things happen sometimes.
I think there's a little more light over here if you're having a hard time. That might be a good place to sit.
Can you see me? Okay, can you hear me?
Of course, if you didn't, you wouldn't answer anyhow. So I guess that's a stupid question to ask if you hear me or not.
But I don't usually use microphones because I don't usually need a microphone.
But it becomes a problem with you having to really attend to hear me, let me know, and I can use a microphone.
But I don't like to use it, and I don't usually have to, and I've lectured in auditoriums this size and bigger without microphones.
And my voice usually lasts, so it should work.
Logistics, there are men and women's restrooms right out to the left.
For those of you that aren't from Mount Carmel, well, not anybody can use them.
I'm telling those of you that aren't from Mount Carmel where the restrooms are.
There are separate restrooms for Mount Carmel people.
But, I have to watch what I say, people take me literally.
Also, there are chips and salsa out there, I guess.
And then tomorrow, Jen's arranged for pizza to be brought in for lunchtime.
And so you can plan on that.
And if you wanted to bring some extra little things to throw on the table, that'd be fine too.
Is that correct?
Correct.
Let's see.
Shannon, anything else I needed to tell them from your information?
We are planning on a outlet, so if you want to get anybody a great baker,
you might want to bring some things back and everything, as far as you want to go.
All right.
Let's see, what else?
Is there any good wing planes around?
Here, do you want to get in?
Maybe Sunday I could spring for wings.
Chris or Apple?
We'll see.
Let me know if there's something really good around here, you know what I mean?
Okay.
I don't know if I'll follow this that well.
All right.
Real quick introduction, then we'll get into it, because you're not here to learn about me.
You're here to learn about the NCLEX RN.
So just so you know a little bit about me, some of you, most of you have never met me,
some of you have taken my class before and are here for a refresher.
So that's cool.
You also can do that.
Let's say that some of you I know are from Wright State and some other places,
and you may not graduate until June-ish.
Somebody may not graduate until June, whatever.
If you keep your receipts, you can come to any other review I have at no cost,
just show your receipt, and you can come.
You know what I'm saying?
So you can keep refreshing, you know, that kind of thing.
All right.
I am a registered nurse.
I have been a nurse since 1973.
So that means I've been a nurse for 36 years.
36 years?
That's all I am.
How old is that year?
So you're born the year I graduated.
Okay.
How many weren't born when I graduated from nurses?
So I've been a nurse for 36 years, so it's been good to me.
It's been a great profession.
I will have to admit that in 1973 in Youngstown, Ohio,
that was the steel mill closings.
We were in a really big recession up there,
and it took me three and a half months to find my first job as a nurse.
But ever since then, I've had a minimum of two jobs going on at the same time.
I've never been unemployed, never lost a job,
always had at least two jobs going on.
So it's a great – even in an economic downtime like it's now,
your first job might be a little hard to find,
but after that, it works pretty well.
So it's been good to me, good to my family.
I love it.
I like to teach it.
So hopefully you'll enjoy it.
I try to stay current as well, you know, in practice, work in nursing,
as well as teach in nursing.
The last two years, I haven't been able to work in nursing
because these reviews have just taken over my life.
Every weekend, I'm somewhere.
Which is – I'm not complaining.
That's great.
It's just I'm going to start saying no to some groups eventually.
Let's see.
I'm basically educated as a med surg nurse,
but I also teach psych, and I worked in psych, so I know psych.
I also do FARM, and I have graduate education in testing and measurement
and cross-cultural nursing, tris-cultural nursing.
Anybody ever hear of Madeline Leininger?
Right state people should have heard of Leininger.
Do you hear her?
She was my advisor, so I'm an expert in cross-cultural and stuff like that.
Let's see.
I worked a lot at ICU, a lot at ER, step-down units.
I usually have the idea that if something scares me, I go at it.
I was scared of neuros, so I first started working in neuros.
Then I was afraid of being able to read EKGs and rhythm strips,
so I went into coronary care and learned that.
Everything – you can learn anything.
Just don't avoid – don't ever think you can't learn something
or that something's too hard for you.
Just go at it, and you'll find that it's not a big deal.
Let's see what else.
I have a wife with four daughters.
Yeah.
I better shut myself off.
It's Friday.
They're teenagers.
They're going to be wanting money.
I better shut up.
Well, there.
Now I want to –
but they always – four daughters, I think.
They're 22, 21, 20, and 12.
So we're just getting out of those teenagers.
But they still do – I had my 20-year-old.
I got a phone call an hour ago from my insurance company.
He said, we have a claim on the state of New York from your daughter
who spun out and hit a mile marker.
And the state of New York has filed a claim on your insurance company
to replace the mile marker.
$1,200.
It's like a mile marker.
Geez.
Give me a break.
That's not what happened with the –
you imagine 20-year-old's insurance is going to go up, too.
But anyhow – okay, I know you care.
Let's see what else.
That's basically it.
I've taught at Cedarwood University for 27 years.
I've taught at nursing there for – this is my 27th year.
And I stick with – I'm sticking them out.
I'm just one town, one job, one wife.
I just sort of stick with them.
I don't like change.
If I could have gotten rid of the kids, I would have been –
I had stuck with them forever.
No, I'm just kidding.
But that's where I am.
So we'll go around the room.
You've got to tell them your name and something.
Nobody else knows about you.
No, we're not going to do that.
You're just going, oh.
Oh, thank goodness.
There's a safe place to do that.
Go to the bathroom, introduce yourself.
We're not doing that, okay?
Forget it.
Okay, what the goal is here, while we're together,
I have three objectives, three objectives.
First, I want you to acquire some knowledge.
I want you to learn something.
I want you to go out that door and go, boy, I learned something today.
Because I don't assume that everybody knows everything.
And it doesn't hurt to learn some new information every once in a while.
And I know enough about nursing to know that every graduate doesn't know
everything they could have done for this board.
There's some information that you need to know for boards that you do not know.
Now, it's different for everybody.
Not everybody has that same deficit.
You have one that someone else doesn't have, and vice versa.
But I want you to acquire some knowledge.
Some reviews, you don't learn anything.
All they do is they just do multiple choice questions.
And you're learning how to apply it.
Well, that assumes you know it.
And you can't apply what you don't know.
So a lot of good it does to sit there and try to apply something if you don't know what they're talking about in the first place.
To me, that's a waste of time.
And I've worked in nursing long enough education to know that students don't know everything that they probably should know.
They've forgotten some stuff.
So we're going to try to spit up your knowledge, and I want you to acquire some knowledge.
Secondly, I want you to gain confidence.
I want you to, when you walk out of here, go, you know, I can do this.
This is something that I can do.
Because I think one of the biggest fears that people have is that they're going to fail.
Because somehow, some way, they're the one person in the universe that this is just beyond their capabilities.
So everybody else will be able to do it.
But they will not.
For some inexplicable reason, it's beyond their capabilities.
And I got through school, and I got through that.
But when I go to the boards, it's just going to get me.
Those standardized tests are just going to get me.
And you don't want to go there.
So I want you to have confidence that you've done everything that you humanly possibly could have done when you sit down to take that board.
Because the worst-case scenario is you go to boards, and you know some of your friends, some of your classmates don't do any reviewing for boards.
They just go take it.
Well, that's okay.
But can you imagine yourself, you sit down for boards, and you sign your name in, and you click go, and it brings up the first question,
and suddenly you realize you haven't done anything to prepare for this?
Can you imagine how you would feel if you had not done a thing to prepare?
Your friends that aren't taking review classes might be confident now.
I'd like to talk to them when that first question pops up and say,
hey, would you think you might want to do something?
But then it's too late.
So when you sit down and start taking that test, I want you to realize that you've done everything you possibly could have done.
And you did what is above and beyond reasonability, and you can have that confidence that you've done your part.
Secondly, I want you to become exam proficient, meaning I want you to know how to take tests,
because earlier I just said you can't apply what you don't know, but you have to be able to apply what you do know.
So it takes three things to pass boards, knowledge, confidence, and skill in taking exams.
So this review is designed to address all three of those points.
Have you acquired some knowledge, gained some confidence, and gained some exam proficiency?
When you walk out of here on Sunday, I want you to think, you know, I know how to do those select all the applies.
I know how to do those click and drags.
I know how to do prioritization questions, delegation questions, staff management questions, best questions, first questions, all those kinds of different formats.
I want you to be able to do point and click in all of those.
So we'll be talking about that.
I really believe that any review, there are two types of reviews out there, and if you've had reviews, you know this.
Is some reviews just sit there and they give you a book that's an outline?
What do they do?
They read it to you.
I don't know about you guys, but I haven't enjoyed being read to since I was seven.
You know?
So I would just immediately go to sleep, and after the first break, I'd probably just leave, figuring I can read it at home underneath somebody to read to me.
And then second, and then the other kind of review is, like I said before, they have to see this whole bank of multiple choice questions.
And all they do is they flash it up on the screen and they say, okay, you got 30 seconds to do this question.
So we're going to sit there, you know, and they say, okay, we're done.
And of course, Susie, aint a retentive over here, says, it's B.
And then all of a sudden now you guys, your thought process is contaminated because she shouted out the answer, and now, do you ever, you know what I'm saying?
And it messes up the whole process, and then you're supposed to learn from that, and then this person starts arguing with the teacher that they didn't think that was the right answer, and then it takes up 20 minutes arguing about some stupid question, and you're going, oh, let me out of here, you know.
This is ridiculous.
What's that?
That's our plan.
Okay. So it just, to me, that doesn't, neither one of those models works.
Because two things, you can't apply what you don't know, but you have to be able to apply what you do know.
And if all they give you is a lecture, you don't get a chance to apply it.
And if all they do is apply it, you don't get a chance to learn it.
So I think the uniqueness about my review, if there is uniqueness, and I believe there is, is that it hits both of those.
I hit a balance between applying and learning, applying and learning.
So that's sort of where we're headed, what we're doing.
Now, with a group this size, we should be able to learn a lot.
I sometimes have groups of 160, 170 people, so it's kind of hard to keep that all.
But sometimes I have groups of 20.
So it just depends.
So this is about a small average size group, which is great.
I like this size.
That way I can keep in contact with you.
Now, I can't really see your eyes very well.
And I always like to make some eye contact every so often.
But please ask questions.
This is your chance to get things clarified.
So ask me questions.
There's probably not a question you could ask me I haven't heard yet.
Because after a while, there's only so many questions people can ask.
So please ask.
If I don't know the answer, I'll tell you where to get it.
Let's see.
Anything else I need to say?
We'll take breaks.
20 minute breaks.
10 minute breaks.
20 minute.
Now, here's the deal.
I always schedule more time for these reviews than I have.
No.
I always schedule more time than I need for these reviews.
So here's the deal.
If 10 minute breaks are 10 minute breaks, we get out.
We'll end up with extra time.
Not because we didn't cover everything, but because the worst thing in a review is not to cover everything.
So I always put an hour or two extra time on every day.
If lunch becomes, instead of 45 minutes or an hour, whatever we decide, it becomes 20 minutes longer than that, then we don't get...
So I'm saying, what am I saying?
To get back in your seat and get...we get started on time, we get out early.
Probably.
Just so I'm saying, most likely.
So you do have control of some of our finish time, our quitting time.
I am assuming, and this is an assumption, you know, that's dangerous.
What did you guys assume about a meal this evening, like 3.30 to 9.30?
Did you plan a meal? Who planned a meal in there?
Who figured we'd just go straight?
So how many figured there was a meal, like four, three or four of you?
Usually on the first day, we don't do a meal.
We just go 10 minute breaks.
Now, isn't there a Wendy's over there or something?
And they can zip over there and grab something and probably eat in here, although you're probably not allowed to have food in here.
They're not going to crab about it, I don't think.
Well, they crab about it.
They won't say anything.
So you can do that.
Just don't squirt, catch up on your neighbor's book.
That's all I would have to say.
Okay, none of that.
But tomorrow we'll have a lunch and Sunday we'll have a lunch.
And lunch, it depends on, sometimes it's a half hour, sometimes it's an hour.
It just depends on where we are and accessibility of food.
Those of you guys that are from this area, Mount Carmel and whatnot,
what would you say is a reasonably prudent amount of time for a group this size to get lunch and to be reasonable to expect them to be back?
Thirty to 40.
Thirty to 40 hours.
What's that?
Just 45 minutes.
We'll start with 45 minutes tomorrow and we'll see how it works.
All righty?
It will be here in a minute.
Okay, I'll plan for that.
All right, and then what we'll do is, if everybody's sitting around doing nothing, well, we'll start early.
That'll mean we'll get out 15 minutes early or we would have otherwise.
Question back here.
Oh, yeah.
When's the next time you're offering a review?
The next scheduled one.
I'm in negotiation with about eight places.
Oh, yeah.
Okay, the next scheduled one is in Florence, Kentucky, south of Cincinnati,
about five to ten minutes south of the airport or five minutes across the street from Turf Way Park.
You've ever been down to play the horses down in Cincinnati?
But it's on March 26, 27, 28.
Supposedly, I'm in negotiation with Ohio State for a review the week before that.
And then I'm in negotiation with Central Ohio Technical College, possibly, for a review sometime mid-March.
And then Chamberlain wants me to come to a review first week of March.
But none of those, those are all Columbus areas.
I also might put in a date and review second or third week of March.
It just depends on how those all come together.
So I can't – the website's the best way to look at – has everybody been to the website?
And that way, as soon as we know something's set, we'll put it on there.
So that's all I can tell you.
I don't know otherwise.
Then there'll be a lot in May, a lot in May.
Any other questions?
Okay, the way this works is basically we play fill in the blank.
You have your yellow book, and that's what we're going to do together.
The blue book is because people for years and years said to me,
what do I do now? What do I do now? Review's over. What do I do now?
What do I do now that it's done? What do I do before, between now and when I take my boards?
And I got tired of telling people individually what to do, so I made this blue book.
I want you to do the blue book.
Doing the blue book is part and parcel of the review.
If you haven't done the review book, you have not done Mark Clemmons' review.
You've only done half of it.
Because that blue book is a drill book to teach you facts.
Facts, facts, facts. When people don't pass boards,
I usually sit down with them when they come to me,
and I'll sit down with them and see if they know what they're talking –
and we'll sit down and start doing some questions.
We probably aren't ten questions into that,
and I've already taken them to the blue book like three or four times.
Because they'll read something and go, oh, I don't know what that is.
Let's get out the blue book.
There it is, page 52. What's it say?
Oh, okay. Well, then it's A. Yeah, it's A.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So get that blue book out.
The first question somebody – on occasion, people will take this course,
not commonly, but on occasion.
People will take this course and not be successful on the boards.
That happens. It happens to every review.
There's no perfect review. If there were a perfect review,
every other review would be out of business.
Do you see what I'm saying?
The other thing is that – so what I do is,
if you would not be successful on your boards
and you would want to talk to me about what to do about it,
do you know what the first question I would ask you would be?
Do you know your blue book?
Do you have your blue book up here?
Okay, then we'll talk.
But you've got to know your blue book first. Then we'll talk.
So it's very important. I can't stress that enough.
Alrighty?
Alright, I think I've covered a variety of issues.
I can cover some things as we go if I've missed anything.
I think most of the logistics are here.
I usually lecture for about an hour and a half before I give a break.
Is that okay?
Your nurses should have developed a bionic bladder.
Yes.
I guess I was just going to ask you more of today's questions.
Every five years, every five years it changes in content.
Every five years in content.
Every three years they review past standards and percentages.
There are going to be a few changes as of April 1 of this – what's that?
Six weeks from today?
There will be a few changes.
But – what's that?
It could be very good for you.
Because the last time, three years – see, every five years they changed content.
And they only changed five percent every five years.
So if they change the content, it's only going to be five percent of the content.
Not the whole content.
You're saying everybody thinks that they changed everything every five years.
Well, that's people that don't know what they're talking about telling you that.
They change five percent every five years.
So in April 1 they will change five percent of the content.
They will drop some issues, include some issues.
My book is designed to get you up until April 1.
And then I have some changes in the book already for after April 1 as well.
But I'm focusing on the 95 percent and not the five.
The other thing is they changed – they re-evaluate the past standard every three years.
And they're going to evaluate that April 1 as well.
And that could be very good for you.
Because the last time they did it, they made it higher.
Now there's some talk that they'll make it higher this time.
But people who really know are saying that they might bring it down.
Because they were getting – they were having too many high – too high a fail rates from schools all over the place.
So I'm saying it used to be Case Western Reserve never had anybody ever fail.
People from their fail.
Christ Hospital's huge high pass rates.
They were having bad times.
She's saying lots of schools that had traditionally done really, really well.
Sinclair Community College in Dayton stayed up pretty well.
But a lot were coming down because they had upped that standard.
So there's a chance they might lower the standard on April 1.
But don't delay taking it until after April 1 because you're thinking they might lower the standard because they may increase it.
So we won't know that until they meet.
But there's a – because the failure rates went up since they changed it three years ago,
there's pressure to bring the standard down.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
All right. Let's talk about acid-base balance in metal layers.
The first lecture.
In the first page you'll notice a table of contents and some page numbers and then some – a blank out to the left.
What that is is that's for you obsessive compulsors to check off the lectures as we go.
Because you have to have some way of knowing that you're accomplishing something.
And if you aren't checking it off a checklist, you're not getting anything done.
So that's for you guys. All right. The rest of us, we won't care.
The other thing about that, too, that's helpful is let's say that tomorrow you are late and you miss two hours of lecturing.
Well, if you're keeping your checklist, you'll know what you've missed and you'll be able to talk to me about it.
And I'll tell you how to get that and how we would arrange for you to get that material you missed.
But if you come up to me and say, I missed yesterday morning. What did I miss?
I'm going to go, I don't remember. You know, I'm just a talking head, basically.
So you keep track of where you're at.
The other thing about this review is we're going to go alphabetical. This is kind of odd.
Because most reviews go by specialty. They'll do all of pharmacology in one day.
And then they'll do all meds, surge in one day, then all peeves in another day, then all psych all at once.
I don't know about you guys, but if I had a five hour review on pharmacology, I would be more confused at the end than I was at the beginning.
Because it just can't dump it like that. So I like to vary it up. And this is, you've had all this stuff before.
So I don't have to teach it in a coherent whole. I can bounce around. And I also want you to get used to bouncing around. Why?
Because what does it do on the test? It bounces around. So I want you to get used to talking about meds, surge, then jump into some psych, then just back to some peeves and then some obi and then bounce around so that your mind understands the principles rather than the specialty.
Got it? Okay. And all you have to do to pass this test is do a little less than average.
How many of you in here, is it possible that you could achieve a little less than average on a test?
See, so you don't have to do how well on this test? Do you have to do well on this test? No. Do you have to do average on this test? No.
You need to do a little less than average on this test to pass. So don't think that you've got some insurmountable standard that you have to hit.
And then you say, well then why do people fail? Because they think they have to be up here. You see what I'm saying? They study that way and they get anxious that way. It just doesn't work.
Okay, acid base is something you do have to know about. If you do not know acid base, you are in trouble because everybody else knows about acid base.
So one thing you have to do in acid base is if they give you an arterial blood gas value report, you have to interpret it as metabolic acidosis, metabolic alkalosis, respiratory acidosis, respiratory alkalosis.
So if they give you lab values, you have to convert it to words. Now if you know how to do that, you're 100% accurate. Go for it. Don't listen to me. I don't want to fix what is it broken.
But if you're confused about that, you're nervous about it, you're anxious about it, I've got something here that might help you. Okay?
Alright, interpreting blood gases. The first thing I suggest you memorize is the rule of the bees. Do you see it there? The rule of the bees.
What I want you to do is fill in here. It says, if the pH, that fills your first blank in. And as I say, there's only 3,000 to go.
So if the pH and the bicarb, the pH and the bicarb are both in the same direction, then it's metabolic.
So the bees are bicarb both bollock. Do you see those? Bicarb both bollock? The reason why this works is respiratory does not have a letter B in it. Bicarb has the B in it.
So what I'm saying is this. They will give you an arterial blood gas with 8 values in it. How many do you look at?
They'll give you 8 values. How many do you look at? 2. Which 2? The pH and the bicarb. That's what the rule says. Just look at the pH, look at the bicarb.
Then look to see what direction they're going. If they're both in the same direction, be it up or down, it doesn't really matter. As long as they're both in the same direction, who cares what direction, then you must use what adjective?
Metabolic. Because the rule says, if the pH and the bicarb are both in the same direction, it's metabolic.
Well, what if they're in different directions? Respiratory. Then you only have one other choice and that's respiratory.
Now, what do you get the acidosis and alkalosis from? The pH. Exactly. So let's look at how this rule would work. Well, first we have to know the normals. What's the normal pH? 7.3 pi, 7.4 pi. That is a piece of universal nursing knowledge. Everyone knows that. If you do not know that, you're the only nurse in the universe that doesn't know it. No, I'm serious.
The normal bicarb is 22 to 26. Not every nurse knows that, so learn that. 22 to 26. I call them the bicarb years when you're 22 to 26 year olds and you have to make all those decisions. What job do I take? Who's my buddy? Am I going to get married? Am I not going to get married? Am I going to move in, not move in?
You know all those decisions you've got to make when you're 22 to 26? That gives you heartburn. So you need the bicarb. I call it the bicarb years because you're always in a knockover of decisions. It's nice to be 56. No choices. No other women watch it. No jobs watches. It's nice. You only got one option. Makes a nice question.
Our teacher told us to remember that 2 plus 2 plus 2 equals 6. That's true, but what does that mean? Oh, 22 to 26. 2, 2, 2, 6. Oh, that's a lot of that. That's good. A lot of 2, so bicarb. So 2, 2, 2, 2, 6. Now, let's look at those and let's look at our examples. In the first example, the pH is in what direction? Down.
So draw a little arrow down in the box next to it. Then the rule says to look at what? The bicarb. And the bicarb in this case is in what direction? Down. So draw a little arrow down. Are those arrows going in the same direction? So what azurant must you use? Metabolic. And because the pH is down, it is. So that is an example of metabolic acidosis.
Okay, look at letter B. Bicarb is in, I mean the pH is in what direction? Up. Bicarb. Up. Are they both in the same direction? Yes. So what azurant must you use? Metabolic. So this is metabolic alkalosis. Wait, is everybody with me?
Okay, the next one. pH is down. Bicarb is up. Are they both in the same direction? No. So what azurant can you not use? Metabolic. Metabolic. So you have to use respiratory. So this would be respiratory. Astastosis.
Now the only time this doesn't work is when there is a mixed acid-base disorder and Bortz doesn't go there. Because that is way too hard.
All right. So does everybody see how the rule works? What if I gave you a pH of 7.50 and a bicarb of 25? 7.50 and 25. What would it be? Respiratory alkalosis. Respiratory alkalosis, why? Because the pH is in what direction? The pH is low.
Well, 7.50 would be up. And the bicarb is? Normal. 25. It's normal. 25. So is that the same direction? Up and normal? So it's got to be respiratory. So even if the bicarb is normal, it still works. You see what I'm saying?
All right. That's the ABG interpretation. Let's talk about signs and symptoms. Letter B.
They will ask, they will tell you a patient has respiratory acidosis, metabolic alkalosis, something like that, and they'll say, what would you see? Select all that apply.
And you've got a whole laundry list to stop and you have to select, check, check, check what's true.
Well, two things here. One thing here, I hate lists. One thing you're going to see in my review is I do not have you memorizing lists of things. I hate lists. I despise lists. I refuse to remember for lists.
The reason why I hated lists in school was two reasons. First reason I hated lists is, for example, if I learned 15 signs of symptoms of hyperkalemia and then 15 signs of symptoms of hypokalemia,
when I took the test, guess what would happen? I'd memorize, I would remember the lists word for word. I could reproduce the lists, but I would forget which one was which.
You see what I'm saying? And when that happens, you're dead. All that work went for nothing.
The second reason why I hated lists was, even if I could remember which was which and all 15 signs, my teachers had the tendency to pick signs numbers 16, 17, 18, and 19, and not the 15 that I memorized.
And one thing that you guys learned really early in nursing is every book says something different, right? Take two nursing books, same thing, look at the list, the lists aren't the same, right?
Have you ever found two lists that were the same for anything in nursing? Never. So you can memorize a whole bunch of lists, but for that to be productive on boards, it better be what? The list that boards is using.
Right? And what chances has that? Very slim. So the point is this boards does not test your knowledge of lists. It does not.
What boards test is your knowledge of principles, not lists. But how will they test your knowledge of principles? By having you generate lists.
Do you understand what I'm saying? Boards will not test your knowledge of what? Lists. They test your knowledge of... but they will test your knowledge of principles by having you generate lists.
And so when people take boards, they say, oh, you got to memorize a whole bunch of lists. No, you don't. They don't know what's going on.
For example, in general, what do pain meds do? In general, what do opioid pain medications do in principle to a person? What do they do? They sedate you, don't they? They're CNS depressants.
Okay, now they will ask a question like, your patient is on Dilaudid and opioid analgesic. What other following things would you expect to see if they got too much or that they were getting a little too much? Select all that apply.
Alrighty. And you're thinking, oh my goodness, I don't remember the list of Dilaudid signs. It's not a list of Dilaudid signs. It's to see if you know that opioid analgesics are CNS-depressive.
So when you go to the list, what do you select? Agitation or lethargy? Lessidity or spasticity? Reflexes of plus one or plus four? Plus one. Hyporeflexia, hyporeflexia. Hyporeflexia. Restlessness or obtundid?
Well, you go, I know what restlessness is. That's up, so obtundid must be down. That's a good test taker right there, okay? And you say, obtundid. A good test taker never says, wha? They say, hmm. And then they figure it out the other way. Think about you guys that aren't good test takers. You haven't figured out that those good test takers, they don't know anything. They're not. They don't know anything more than you know. In fact, they probably know less than you know.
They just don't quit. They just figure, oh, I'll get it. They won't let me in the front door, I'll go in the back door. If the back door's closed, I go through the cellar window. And they'll figure a way to get out of it. They just don't quit. Poor test takers go, oh, I don't know what that is. No. I just do that. It was a really bad test taker. He came to a maternity question and it said, what's the best way to treat morning sickness in a first-time Mr. Woman? And he said, oh, this is the only OB-AD question I know the answer to.
It's crackers. He was so excited and he got the one OB thing he did not. So it's crackers, crackers. It looks A didn't say crackers, B didn't say crackers, C didn't say crackers, and D didn't say crackers. And what did he say? It's a bad test taker. What did he say? Oh my goodness. I thought I knew this. I guess I don't know this. So he'd pick something like antacids every half hour. Okay. And then he wonders why he doesn't do very well.
Well, you know what number C said? You know what answer number C said? Dry carbohydrates. Well, the shot is in dry carbohydrates. Cracker. But what did he do? You know, he was expecting the front door. Cracker. No, you go to the back door. Dry carbohydrates. You see what I'm saying? Don't give up. Don't think that you don't know this. You know it. Okay. So if they say, restless versus obtundant, you know what restless is. Obtundant must be the ego.
Obtundant must be the other. Okay. But do you see what I'm saying about the sedation? And you generate the list by applying the what? Principle, not having memorized some list. Does that make sense? Do you see why boards can't, why can't boards test lists? Why can a national nursing test not test lists? Because what? All the lists are different. You can't test lists.
Because what? All the lists are different in different textbooks used in different geographical areas of the nation. So write a statistically significant, reliable, valid question. You have to write the question so that no matter who takes it, no matter what books they read, no matter what school they went to, it's a fair question.
And if you're just taking out of most of these books on whatever, the signs and symptoms of whatever, and you write a question on that, it will perform horribly, statistically, nationally. The only way you can do these select all that applies and have them perform well is to test what? Principles and see if a student can generate a list from a principle.
Now does that change the way you might look at a select all that apply question? You understand what they're about? There is no mystery. You weren't supposed to have memorized some mystery list that you didn't know. You're supposed to say, this is a chance for me to show I know a principle. You got that? That's how you do those.
Okay. So I want to give you a principle for answering acid-based signs and symptoms. And it's what's in the box there. It says, as the PH goes, so goes my patient. As the PH goes, so goes my patient. What? What does that mean? As the PH goes?
The PH can go up or the PH can go down. And when the PH goes up, your patient goes up. And when the PH goes down, your patient goes, does that mean they sink and levitate? What does that mean? What's it mean?
So when the PH goes up, every system in your body gets more irritable. But when your PH goes down, systems in your body shuts down. So when your face goes down, you shut down. When your PH goes up, everything gets hyper excitable. It's pure chemistry.
It's talking about catalyzing chemical reactions, basically. So do you see where it says, oh, except for potassium. Sorry, I didn't write that in there. Except for potassium. So what does that mean?
The PH goes up, potassium goes down.
And when the PH goes down, potassium goes up. Because if it followed the rule, we wouldn't even mention it, right? So as the PH goes, so goes my patient, except for potassium.
So if your patient goes up, do you see the little box there that says up? What is that, what's another name for that? Up PH?
Alkalosis.
What will you see with alkalosis? Give me some stuff. Give me some signs. Do you see with alkalosis? Irritability. Irritability, absolutely. Hyperreflexia. What would be some numbers that would be hyperreflexic? What numbers?
Three and four. Three and four are hyper. Two is normal. One and zero are hypo. Remember that with reflexes? Three and four are high, hyper. Two is normal.
Reflex and one to zero is hyporeflex. What else would you see with alkalosis?
You've got two of them.
We've got irritable, we've got hyperreflexia. What else do you think? Think of a body system and then go a high.
Tachypnea. What else?
Tachycardia.
Would you have paralytic ilius or borberigmia?
Good. You could test take or say borberigmia even though you may not know what it is because paralytic ilius sounds like everything's shuttin' down. That would be the down, the up would be borberigmia.
Now, Bords loves the word borberigmia. B-O-R-B-O-R-Y-G-M-I. That is the word they will use for increased vowel sounds.
So if you hear somebody stomach growling this evening, what will you say?
Borberigmia.
Borberigmia, increased vowel sounds.
Can you spell that one more time?
B-O-R, and do it again, B-O-R-Y-G-M-I. Borberigmia.
So what would be down?
Acetosysin. What would you see there?
What's that?
Hyporeflexia.
What else?
Bradycardia.
Lefurgy.
By the way, obtundid means just one step more lethargic than lethargy.
Obtundid. Vocabulary is critically important to pass this test. That's why the blue book and the yellow book are real heavy on vocab.
Can't answer a question if you don't know what the words mean. Sounds pretty obvious.
So what would you have? Paralytic ilius or borberigmia?
Paralytic ilius.
Would they have a seizure or a coma?
Coma.
Seizure is up, coma is down. Gotta go the same as the B-H.
So let me ask you this. What acid-based imbalances are most likely to seize and which ones are most likely to have a respiratory arrest?
Aqualosis.
Aqualosis will what?
Seize.
Seize and?
Acidosis.
Acidosis will?
Respiratorily.
Respiratorily arrest.
Does that make sense? Because you're doing it as the pH goes, so goes your patient.
So what acid-based disorders need an ambo bag at the bedside?
What acid-based imbalances need an ambo bag at the bedside?
Acidosis.
Acidosis because they're going to what? Respiratorily arrest.
Which acid-based disorders need suction machines at the bedside?
Apples.
Apples because they could seize and aspirate.
See, don't limit yourself. When they start asking these things, they say, wait a minute, I know about this. I can get there.
See, I shouldn't have to teach you who needs an ambo bag at the bedside.
You should be able to get that from as the pH goes, so goes my patient.
Do you see what I'm saying?
These rules, use them. They're tools.
Okay.
Before we turn the page, I want to ask you, I'm going to introduce you to, whoa.
Don't look at the light.
Does that come in clear?
Oh, duh.
I want to introduce you to my favorite Scotsman.
Now Scottish surnames have Mac, Google, McDonough, MacGyver, M.A.C.
My favorite Scotsman, Matt Kuzma.
How many have heard of Kuzma?
Okay. From now on, I want you to, every time you see Kuzma, I want you to think, why?
Matt Kuzma.
In fact, if you're talking to a doctor and he goes, he's Matt Kuzma, I'll be happy.
It'll make them look stupid, but I'll be happy.
The reason is, is Kuzmals is a compensatory respiratory pattern for one and only one acid-base disorder.
You only see Kuzmals with one of the four metabolic disorders, one of the four acid-base disorders.
Which one? Well, Mac tells you that. M for what?
M.A.C.
And A.C. for acidosis.
So, Mac Kuzma tells you that you see Kuzmals with metabolic acidosis.
Okay, we have some knowledge, but we have to be able to what?
Apply it.
Remember, you can't apply what you do not know, but what you know you have to be able to apply.
This says, your patient has respiratory acidosis, select all and apply.
Plus one, three, flex six.
Diarrhea.
A. Dynamic Ilius.
Spasm.
Urinary retention.
Paroxysmal.
Atrial.
Tachycardia.
Second degree.
Mobis.
Type II.
Arculum.
And hypo-phalemia.
I want you guys to get in groups two and three, right where you're sitting, you have to move.
I want you to talk to somebody, your buddy, and I want you to answer this question.
And I want you to use the rule that I taught you.
The rule is what?
As the BH goes, so goes my patient except for potassium.
Now, I really want you to draw some arrows here.
I want you to draw arrows.
And I want you to get the answer.
So you can do it yourself and turn to your buddy, discuss it, and then we'll talk about it.
And don't say any answers out loud.
All right.
So we're choosing which one.
It means select all that apply.
So we're choosing what is respiratory acidosis.
All right.
Knowing that as the pH goes, so goes my patient.
And as the pH goes down, so goes down.
I'm going to say that.
I really want you to go up with this.
Plus one repletting, plus one repletting would be down, so it would be that.
Yeah.
Adding not anomic.
That would be high.
So that is a good.
I hope a lean.
Wait a minute.
Now that's different, though.
That's that's except for potassium.
So if it goes down, that means the potassium is up.
So.
So I guess it would be down, low is down.
So it would probably be that.
I want you to count the number of things selected.
Don't say it yet, but I'll ask for it later.
I will count the number you selected.
Down is zero to one.
Zero to one.
So that is when we would check the repletting.
Two is normal.
Okay, how many did you select?
Three.
I got three.
I know I don't know.
How many did you select?
Three.
You should have selected four.
So let's play our game.
What did you automatically notice about this question?
You said what?
Acidosis.
Acidosis is in what direction?
Down.
Acidosis is going to go in the same direction, which is what direction?
Except for potassium, which is going to go?
Up.
So a high K.
So now there's your answer.
Down.
Up or down?
Select or no select?
Yes.
Up or down?
Select or no select?
No.
Adynamic without movement?
Up.
Up or down?
Down.
Select or no select?
Select.
Spasm, up or down?
Select or no select?
No.
Urinary retention?
Down.
Select.
Carves says, well, April Ticardis, select or no?
No.
Movis, type two, heart block, yes or no?
Yes.
Why?
Block means the impulse is being what?
Slowed.
Blocked.
It's down.
It's being hindered.
So that's a select.
Hypokalemia?
No.
I want a high K.
Not a low K.
So the answer is the plus one reflects the adynamic illness of the urinary retention
and the second degree of Movis, type two, heart block.
How many got that right?
Excellent.
Did you memorize the list?
No.
How long would the list be before you got second degree of Movis, type two, heart block?
Right?
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's what, and they're testing what principle?
What principle are they testing?
Then in an acidotic environment, chemical reaction seeks.
So everything shuts down and that's why you do it.
See?
You weren't supposed to have memorized these.
Do you see what my point is?
So this should kind of free you from the fear of these select all that applies.
Well, by the way, what's the number one mistake that people make with select all that apply?
Most common mistake made was select all that apply questions.
Not even counting.
Selecting one more than you should have selected.
Number one problem.
Now, those of you who are real concrete people, I did not say answer what you think and take away one.
Okay?
I didn't say that.
I said that the tendency for people is to answer what?
One more than they should.
Should.
So here's the deal with a select all that apply, if you know it's two of them, what do you do?
Select those two and what?
Stop.
Because if you go, well, you know it could be, oh, okay.
Now that's a killer on select all that apply.
It could be, don't go there with select all that apply.
That is not cool because you're heading down a road that's going to get you too wrong.
If you do not know that it's an apply, do not answer select all of them.
You know what I'm saying?
If you don't know that this is true, then don't pick it.
Does that make any sense?
All right.
The other thing about select all that apply, it's never only one and it's never all of them.
You know what I'm saying?
Never answer just one on a select all that apply and don't answer all of them on a select all that apply because it's never one and it's never all of them.
Okay.
Let's go to the next page.
Causes of acid-base amounts.
Causes.
What they'll do is they'll give you a scenario and they'll say, this is what's happening to your patient.
They'll say, what acid-base disorder would result from this?
Do you see they're flipping it around.
Instead of saying, what sign and symptom will the acid-base balance cause, they're asking, what will cause the acid-base amount?
And one thing that people do wrong when they answer these kinds of questions is they get signs and symptoms and causation messed up.
Do you realize that in the human body, oftentimes what causes something is the opposite of what the signs and symptoms of that thing are?
Does everybody understand what I'm saying?
So a lot of times what will happen is diarrhea will cause a metabolic acidosis.
But once you get acidotic, it will shut your bowels down and you will get a paralytic illness.
Do you see what diarrhea caused the paralytic illness results from?
It's the opposite.
And when you're sitting there going, man alive, I learned it was this and now you're telling me the opposite, probably what are you messing up?
Causation.
Causation versus sign and symptoms.
So make sure that you, many times if you go back and you do questions now and you get confused, think, wait a minute, wait a minute, are you talking about sign and symptom or are they talking about causation?
Then you can go, oh, I see where the problem is.
Does everybody understand that?
Okay.
So just keep that straight.
Having said that, we're talking about causation now.
Whenever you get a scenario, the first big question you ask yourself is, is it lung?
That goes in the first blanch.
Is it lung?
L-U-N-G.
Is the scenario a lung scenario?
If the scenario they give you is a lung scenario, guess what kind of a problem it is?
Respiratory.
It's respiratory.
I mean, it can't be any easier than that.
However, that only gives you a 50-50 because it could be a respiratory acidosis or a respiratory apolysis, correct?
Right.
Well, how do you tell between those?
Well, the second question you ask yourself is, is the client overventilating or underventilating?
Is the client or patient overventilating or underventilating?
That is going to be critical for your respiratory.
If the patient is overventilating, pick alkalosis.
If they are underventilating, pick acidosis.
Now, this is extremely simple.
It's almost pathetically simple.
These are not the only four options you have to choose from when you combine them to make these imbalances.
It's either metabolic or respiratory.
It's either acidosis or arcolysis, right?
So you're choosing between these four words, correct?
Well, let's look to see how this works.
If the client is overventilating, let's take the word ventilating.
Which of these three words fits best with the idea of ventilating?
Exactly.
Now, we're left with what?
Over.
Of the remaining three words, which word has the closest connection to something being over?
Why alkalosis?
Because it's over the normal.
So that's alkalosis.
So if you put them together, ventilating over becomes respiratory alkalosis.
See how easy that is?
And if I say the patient is underventilating, what does that become?
Respiratory.
What does under become?
Acid.
Acid, because that's under the normal.
So undervent becomes respiratory acidosis.
You see, you're just translating.
You're just translating.
See that?
How many understand what I'm saying?
Do you see how easy this is?
You're simply translating.
So when they say overventilating, you say, oh, respiratory alkalosis.
Underventilating, respiratory acidosis.
So let me ask you this.
They give you a scenario where a woman is overzealously using her breathing techniques during labor.
She's really overzealously using those breathing techniques.
What acid-base disorder would she exhibit?
Well, is that lung?
Yes, she's over breathing techniques.
Overzealousy using breathing.
So that's lung.
Is she overventilating or underventilating?
Overventilating.
You translate that to mean respiratory alkalosis, and that would be your answer.
You have a child who was a victim of near drowning.
What acid-base disorder would it be?
Well, is that a lung scenario, near drowning?
Yes.
Would the kid have been overventilating or underventilating when he was nearly drowning?
Under.
Under, so he would have respiratory acidosis.
Your patient has emphysema and air trapping.
Is that lung?
Yes.
Is he overventilating or underventilating?
Under.
Under, so he would respiratory acid-base disorder.
Be careful.
Ventilating doesn't mean respiratory rate.
The respiratory rate is irrelevant here.
Everybody pays way too much importance to the respiratory rate.
Do you understand that ventilation has to do with gas exchange, not respiratory rate?
For example, I could say that a person had pneumonia in five lobes of their, four lobes of the lung.
Pneumonia in four lobes.
They're breathing at 50 a minute, and their SAO2 is 78 on eight liters per mask.
What do they have?
Pneumonia in four lobes.
They're breathing really fast, but their SAO2 is really low.
Now, is that person overventilating or underventilating?
Under, even though their rate is 50, because rate has nothing to do with it.
And everybody pays so much attention to rate, they miss these questions right and left, and don't understand why.
Because you're paying attention to the wrong piece of information.
It's not about the rate, it's about the SAO2.
Would you agree with me that if your SAO2 is good, and you're breathing slow, you're fine,
but if you're breathing faster and your SAO2 is low, you're actually underventilating?
So the rate can be tricky.
So what am I trying to tell you?
When you get asked the base disorder questions, what piece of data in the question is real shaky to use to get your answer?
Respiratory rate.
Because a lot of times it compensates, which means does the opposite, so you'll totally get the wrong answer.
You see what I'm saying?
Pay attention to what?
SAO2.
Somebody's on a PCA pump.
What acid-base imbalance would tell you that maybe they need to come off that thing?
They're on a PCA pump.
What acid-base disorder would tell you they need to maybe come off that thing?
Well, you say, okay, well, PCA pump, what do we know about PCA pumps?
Depressed.
Despressed.
Respirations.
Why would they need to come off of it if they were getting too much, which would make my respiratory rate go really what?
My ventilations go really down, which would mean I would be underventilating, so the answer would be respiratory acidosis.
So respiratory acidosis would tell you that maybe you need to back off that PCA pump.
Is that making sense?
And see, those are questions you may not have even thought you know the answer to, but you can get the answer if you just calm down and use it.
Because this is a what?
It's a tool.
So use the tools if you're just both.
Don't say, I can't get the screw out and the screwdriver's still sitting in the box.
Now grab the screwdriver and try to get it out.
So many times I teach people tools on how to take tests and everything, and then I do test questions with them and they leave the tools in the box.
You know what I'm saying?
Get the tools out.
Start using them.
What if it's not lung?
The next box says, what if it isn't lung?
It's metabolic.
Then it's metabolic.
If it isn't lung, it's metabolic.
Well, good news.
There's really only one scenario where you will answer metabolic alkalosis, and that's what the next fill in the blank says.
It says, if the patient has prolonged gastric vomiting or suctioning, pick metabolic alkalosis.
Why?
Why does prolonged gastric vomiting and suctioning lead to metabolic alkalosis?
You're losing acid.
If you lose acid, you become basic.
Otherwise, everything else that isn't lung, you pick metabolic acidosis.
For everything else that isn't lung, that's another fill in the blank.
For everything else that is not lung, pick metabolic acidosis.
So let me ask you this.
The patient had GI surgery.
He has had an NG tube to low intermittent gong co-suctioning for three days.
What acid-base disorder would he most likely exhibit?
Metabolic alkalosis.
Your patient has hyperemesis gravidarum.
What acid-base disorder are they most likely to exhibit?
Metabolic alkalosis.
Your patient with hyperemesis gravidarum is now dehydrated.
What acid-base disorder would they have?
Now they've gotten dehydrated.
That's not prolonged gastric vomiting suctioning.
It's something you see with it, but it isn't what it is.
So now what would they have?
Metabolic acidus.
Because that's what caused that.
Yeah, it flipped on the other side and now you're there.
Good point.
What about this person who has acute renal failure?
What acid-base disorder?
Acute renal failure.
Why metabolic acidosis?
Why?
You're right, but why?
Is it lung?
No.
Is it vomiting or suctioning?
So it's got to be metabolic acidosis.
Is everything that isn't lung or vomiting or suctioning is metabolic acidosis.
So what about infantile diarrhea?
What acid-base disorder?
Metabolic acidosis.
Metabolic acidosis, why?
It's not lung and it's not vomiting.
That's the other end.
Diarrhea.
What about third degree burns over 60% of the body?
Third degree burns over 60% of the body, first phase?
What?
Absolutely, metabolic acidosis because it's not what?
Lung.
And it's not vomiting or suctioning.
Okay, what do you, what acid-base disorder do you see with idiopathic bullus pempoigus?
What?
Metabolic acidosis.
Yeah, metabolic acidosis is very good.
Why?
Because it's not lung.
I mean, I don't know what it is.
It is lung though.
But if it is lung, I mean, you know, it's only, you got one body system out of 13.
Right?
And if it's lung or suctioning, you've got one out of a thousand symptoms.
So when you don't know what it is, what's your answer?
Absolutely, metabolic acidosis.
Everybody, right now.
Right now, as you're sitting there, I want you to set your default setting for answering acid-base questions to metabolic acidosis.
Okay, everybody do it.
Okay?
Do it.
So that when you, what do I never want to hear?
I never want to hear you guys go, oh, I don't know what acid-base disorder is because I've never heard of that disease.
That's when you absolutely do know what it is.
It's what?
I've used that word, that rule for 20 years.
I take the NSC twice a year.
I take ATIs.
I take Kaplan junk.
No, stop.
She doesn't say junk.
What?
Kaplan quality materials.
And I do every book that's published, everything that's there, I do that.
Why do I do it?
It's my job to prepare for you guys.
You know what I mean?
I better know what's out there and I better know what's current and I better know what's, you know,
how it's being tested.
So I've done, if it's been published, I've done it.
I've even been to the NCSBN site and done their questions.
So I know what these questions, and every time I don't know on an acid-base question what does Mark Clemmons think?
And he's 100% right everything.
I have never missed a question using that.
All right?
So let me ask you this.
What do you have to know for acid-base?
Well, what you have to know is if the pH and the bicarb are both in the same direction, it's metabolic.
As the pH goes to those of my patients except for potassium, macchusmal, overventilate, underventilate,
translate, vomiting or suction, metabolic alkalosis, everything else is metabolic acidosis.
If I don't know what's a big metabolic acidosis, that's acid-base.
It's all you need to know.
So say it with me.
If the pH and the bicarb are both in the same direction, it's metabolic.
As the pH goes, so goes my patient except for potassium.
Who's your favorite Scotland?
Okay.
Overventilate, underventilate, translate.
What do I mean by that?
Yeah, translate.
There are overventilators, respiratory alkalosis, underventilators, respiratory acidosis.
If it's vomiting or suctioning, pick.
Metabolic alkalosis for everything else, pick.
Metabolic acidosis, when you don't know what's a pick, pick.
Yeah, I use that all the time.
Those are the same.
I use that all the time.
That works for you.
Those are helpful tools that work.
All right.
Yes?
So just to make this clear, that one question you asked, if you have severe vomiting
and you've gotten dehydrated now, that you look at the dehydration.
Dehydration, right.
So now it's...
There's a rule in test-taking.
So watch what they're asking.
When you want to get a question right, you always pay more attention to the modifying
phrase than the original noun.
Everybody hear that?
You always pay more attention to the modifying phrase than the original noun.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So a person with obsessive compulsive disorder who is now psychotic, what's more important?
Psychotic than obsessive compulsive.
Do you see what I'm saying?
A patient with vomiting who is now dehydrated, the dehydrated takes precedence over.
So the modifying phrase trumps original noun.
And people get caught on that every time.
Boku questions.
They've crashed and burned on that because they're focusing on original noun.
It's gone past original noun.
It's now modifying phrases what the question's about.
Good question.
Okay, let's talk about ventilation.
We'll take a break.
Ventilation.
The first two things you have to know is the alarms.
You have to know the alarm systems.
And you have to know how the blood gases articulate with ventilators.
There is a thing called a high pressure alarm.
A high pressure alarm is triggered by increased resistance to air flow.
Increased resistance to air flow.
In other words, the machine is having to push too hard to get the air into the lungs.
It's having to push too hard.
There's resistance.
And when that happens, the machine will set off a high pressure alarm.
Because you understand, when you set up events, you set up two alarms.
You say, I don't want you to use less than this pressure to get that air in.
And I don't want you to use any more than that pressure.
You tell it that.
And then when it exceeds that, the high pressure alarm does help.
See, if you set the high pressure at 40 millimeters of mercury, you say, I don't want you to push.
Machine, I don't want you to push any more than 40 millimeters of mercury to get that air in.
If the machine has to, it will set off the high pressure alarm.
Because it's telling you it's too hard.
I'm having to work too hard because it's high pressure.
Does everybody understand that conceptually?
Okay, now, what would it be due to?
Well, obstructions.
There are three obstructions.
Number one, kinks in the tubing.
The tubing could be kink.
Would that increase resistance?
Sure.
So what do you do for that?
That's rocket science, unkink.
Okay, then, second most common obstruction is water condensing within the tube.
There's water condensing in the dependent loops.
So what do you do for that?
Now, there are more rocket science here.
Empty it.
And the third most common cause is mucus secretions in the airway.
They've got gook there.
Don't.
Jump.
Mucus.
And what do you do for that?
Now, what will be suction is correct, but what would you do before you suction?
And I'm not talking about preoxygenating, because that is true,
but is there another strategy that would be done to mobilize secretions before you would actually suction the person?
What would you do?
Yeah, change position.
Turn, cop, debrief.
Change position.
So you would do that first, and if that didn't work, what would you do?
Suction.
What do you guys know about suctioning airways?
What do you think?
Good, bad, otherwise, what do you think?
Give me your impression.
The more you do it, the more secretions problems you cause, so it's a double-edged sword.
So how often do you suction patients?
Every 15 minutes, every hour, every two hours, every four hours, or none of the above?
None of the above.
How often do you suction people?
That's unnecessary, and that means when they cannot mobilize it after they've been turned and cop and debrief.
In ICU, I'm notorious for beginning nurses always negatively talk about me in ICUs,
because I don't do much suctioning, but I do an awful lot of turning.
And I find if somebody's O2 sat low, and they're tacking, and they're looking like they need to,
and they're, I don't get good air exchange, and the high-pressure alarms are going off all the time, I turn them.
Patient coughs and whack, the outcomes of this thing hit the wall on the other side, you know?
And then they pick up, and they're just fine, thank you, and I never did suction them.
And I'll go in and report, and they'll say, how many times did you suction them?
I didn't suction them at all.
How come you never suctioned people?
Well, his O2 sat is 98 on room air.
You got a problem with this?
He's going to say, his lungs are clear.
He's got 98 on room air.
Temperature is normal.
You got a problem?
Okay? So I do a lot of turning, man.
I do a lot of turning and confident deep breathing, and I find I will do a whole lot of suctioning.
Some people, yeah, but not as much.
Okay, so that would be a click and drag.
What do I mean by a click and drag?
Order.
What would you do first?
High-pressure alarm goes off.
What do you do first?
What do you click first?
Unkink.
Check for kinks and unkink.
Click it, drag it, drop it.
Then what would you grab second?
Empty water out of tubing.
Click, drag, drop.
Then what?
Turn, copy, breathe, click, drag, drop.
Suction.
Click, drag, drop.
That would be your order.
Turn the page and let's talk about low-pressure alarms.
What's this saying?
Decreased resistance.
Remember I told you you always set a low level,
and if it is below that, there's decreased resistance.
So what did the machine say?
That was too easy, yeah.
I had to work too little.
That was way too easy pushing that breath in.
Well, what do you think would cause a low-pressure alarm?
Decreased resistance.
Disconnections.
There are two disconnections you need to know about.
The first one is disconnection of the main tubing.
If the main tubing is disconnected, what do you do?
Reconnect.
Yeah, it's more rocket-sized.
The other most common disconnection is the oxygen sensor tubing.
What is the oxygen sensor tubing?
What is that?
Anybody know?
It senses the FIO2 right at the trach area
or the airway area.
What's it look like?
Anybody know what it is?
It comes from the ventilator machine.
It's a wire, a black coated wire.
It's very small.
It's probably about half the diameter of your pencil or pen
that you're using there.
And it goes right along the tubing, piggyback in it,
along the tubing, and it comes right where the trach or the endo tube is,
and it kind of just hooks.
Do you have a computer where when your battery's low,
you take the cord in, you hook that little cord in there,
makes a right angle, you have one like that?
Well, it's like that.
It hooks into that hole in the tubing.
It measures the FIO2, the oxygen delivered right there.
But if that pops off, when the air comes in, what's it do?
It goes out that tube instead of into them, and there's less resistance.
Do you see how that would work?
So you have to just take that sensor and plug it back in.
Because so many nurses, they'll be going bong, bong, bong, low pressure,
and they're going, but it's connected.
It's connected, and here's the wire hanging down, and they don't see it.
So reconnect the main tubing, then reconnect the oxygen sensor.
Those are the two most common problems.
So in general, what are high pressure alarms due to?
In general, obstructions.
In general, what are low pressure alarms due to?
Disconnections.
In LPNs, this is the same as RN.
You understand the RN test?
LPN is the same information.
It's just from a different perspective.
For example, like an RN question would say,
you have the following four patients, which one would you assign to an LPN?
The LPN question would say, you have the following four patients,
which one would you accept as an assignment from an RN?
It's the exact same four people just looking at it the other way.
You see what I'm saying?
So you really do, LPNs and RNs need to know basically the same kinds of things.
They just need to know the difference in the scope of that practice.
In some ways, no, I won't go there.
Okay.
What about acid-base disorders?
Respiratory alkalosis.
Respiratory alkalosis means the ventilator settings may be to what?
Why did you say that?
We can turn respiratory alkalosis into another word.
What can we turn it into?
Respiratory.
Ventilate.
Alkalosis.
Over.
So then you write and read it.
Overventilating means the ventilator settings may be to...
See how easy it is?
All you do is take these acid-base disorders, turn them into just normal words,
and the answer will jump off the page at you.
So what is the other word for respiratory acidosis?
Underventilate.
Underventilating means the settings are to...
Low.
Do you got that?
Now how would this be applied in a question?
And this will do this question then go to a break.
The doctor says wean off vent in AM.
Got it?
He's writing it today for tomorrow.
Wean the patient off the ventilator in the morning tomorrow.
The 6 AM ABGs show respiratory acidosis.
What would you do?
A. Follow the order.
B. Call respiratory therapy.
C. Hold the order.
Call doctor.
Or D. Begin to decrease the settings.
What would you do?
Talk to your buddy.
Call...
In LPNs it would be wherever it says...
Wherever it says call doctors you can put notified RN.
What's your answer?
C.
The answer is C. Why did you know it was C?
Underventilating.
He's underventilating.
How do you know he's underventilating?
Government's
He's on the ventilator and he's already underventilated on the ventilator.
Am I going to take him off the ventilator?
No.
He's going to be even worse.
So what acid-base disorder did you want to see at 6 AM?
Respiratory
Alkalosis.
Alkalosis, which means he's being overventilated.
In that case he probably doesn't need a ventilator.
So is this hard or easy?
An hour ago, I told you, you've got to get a bunch of questions on ventilators and acid-base
and how do you use your acid-base imbalances to know what to do with ventilators.
How many would be going, oh my goodness.
How many would you see?
He's not really hard.
He's very simple.
You can be with the acid-base.
Why is B a bad answer?
What's that?
Yeah, never pick an answer where you don't do something and somebody else has to do something.
You may feel like doing that, but that isn't the answer.
Okay, that's what I call the chicken answer.
You know, you're trying to, you're spraying the call so you have respiratory therapy to it.
But the patient says to you, I have cancer.
I only have six months to live.
Do you think there's a heaven or a hell?
Where do you think I'll go when I die?
What would you do?
Do not pick call chaplain.
Now you may not feel like you want to deal with that right then and right there,
but as a nurse you're supposed to say what?
What do you think about it?
Do you see what I'm saying?
Not the answer.
Yeah, you're going to hell.
How to make a fear?
Yeah, I can see that.
Don't tell anybody to see it while I say that.
Okay, take a 10 minute break.
You guys have been really good.
And we'll come back at 25 after.
What you may have found out there is you know some of the things that you're going to see in general.
Is the question where you're failing, are those organ questions that they say?
Here in New Parliament, they'll be able to just part of you prior to giving Parliament help.
What do you think about the situation?
I think you guys have been on a very tight line.
You missed that.
You're going to be on that?
You never have to show.
Do you see a situation where I think you see a certain amount of people who are going to say,
I have to accept it.
What would you do first?
I don't know.
You can take the beauty of my day, take the temperature, take your blood pressure, take your clothes.
Do you see the trouble?
What would you do first?
Did you write the one down about the guy with third degree burns or six percent of her body?
He had metabolic blood.
Well, I think it's a little gentrallist.
I think it's a little gentrallist.